<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Addresses | Full Stack Snacks]]></title>
  <link href="http://MProuts.github.io/blog/categories/addresses/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://MProuts.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-21T13:04:59-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://MProuts.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Prouty]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Addressing IP]]></title>
    <link href="http://MProuts.github.io/blog/2014/07/15/addressing-ip/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-15T11:44:20-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://MProuts.github.io/blog/2014/07/15/addressing-ip</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The Basics</h3>

<p>TCP/IP (or Transmission Control Protocol/Internet Protocol) is the most ubiquetous inter-network protocol in use today.  Computers use
TCP/IP to connect to other networks as well as to the internet.  An IP
address is a unique identifier for a device connected to a TCP/IP
network.</p>

<p>IP addresses consists of four eight-digit binary numbers or <em>octets</em>
(also called <em>bytes</em>), usually represented in base-10 notation, and
separated by periods.</p>

<h4>Example Binary Representation</h4>

<blockquote><p>1100000 10101000 00000001 00110110</p></blockquote>

<h4>Example Base-10 Representation</h4>

<blockquote><p>192.168.1.54</p></blockquote>

<h3>Reserved Addresses</h3>

<p>Some addresses are reserved for particular purposes.  A list follows:</p>

<p><strong>0.0.0.0</strong> is reserved for the <strong>Default Route</strong>, meaning that address
lookups that do not match any route known to the network fall back to
this address.  It typically points to the default gateway &mdash; the node on
the network (often your router) that serves as the point of access for connecting to
other networks or the internet.</p>

<p><strong>255.255.255.255</strong> is reserved for <strong>Network Broadcasts</strong>.  Messages
sent to this address go to all computers on the network.</p>

<p><strong>127.0.0.1</strong> is the most commonly-used <strong>Loopback Address</strong>, which is
an address your computer uses to refer to itself.  Messages sent from your computer to this address echo back to your computer.  The hostname &lsquo;localhost&rsquo; resolves to this address.</p>

<h3>Private IP Addresses</h3>

<p>The TCP/IP protocol was devised in the 1970s before the internet took
off.  The specification for IPv4 addresses (as opposed to the newer
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv6">IPv6</a>) only provides for <code>256 ^ 4</code> or
<code>4,294,967,296</code> unique addresses.  If every internet-enabled device was
assigned a unique address, the pool of unique addresses would have been
exhausted long ago.</p>

<p>Realizing this, back in 1996, the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)
specified special blocks of <em>private IP addresses</em> &mdash; i.e. addresses that
could not be used over the internet.  This way, groups of internet-enabled
devices could share a single globally-unique public IP address through a
router, while maintaining separate private IP addresses to communicate
amoungst themselves on a local network.  The uniqueness of a private IP address
is only enforced amoung devices on a given local network, thus many devices
can simultaneously use the same local IP address on separate local networks.</p>

<p>Reserved private IP address ranges are as follows:</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th style="font-size:.8em">Class</th>
  <th style="font-size:.8em">Address Range</th>
  <th style="font-size:.8em">Leading Bits</th>
  <th style="font-size:.8em">CIDR Notation</th>
  <th style="font-size:.8em">Unique Addresses</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>A</td>
  <td>10.0.0.0 - 10.225.225.225</td>
  <td>00001010</td>
  <td>10.0.0.0/8</td>
  <td style="text-align:right">16,777,216</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>B</td>
  <td>172.16.0.0 - 172.31.255.255</td>
  <td>10101100 0001</td>
  <td>172.16.0.0/12</td>
  <td style="text-align:right">1,048,576</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>C</td>
  <td>192.168.0.0 - 192.168.255.255</td>
  <td>11000000 10101000</td>
  <td>192.168.0.0/16</td>
  <td style="text-align:right">65,536</td>
</tr>
</table>


<br>


<p>Since the number of computers connected to a LAN is typically much
smaller than 65,536, most routers limit their IP assignments to 255
addresses in the range 192.168.0.1 &ndash; 192.168.0.255.</p>

<p>If you check your private IP address under network preferences (assuming you&rsquo;re
on a Mac), it is probably in the form &lsquo;192.168.0.X.&rsquo;</p>

<h3>Public IP Addresses</h3>

<p>If you google
<a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=what+is+my+ip+address">&lsquo;what is my ip address&rsquo;</a>,
you will quickly find your router&rsquo;s public IP address.  This will be the same for
every device connected to your LAN.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
